Finding Aid for the James Merrill Safford Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
James Merrill Safford Collection
1889-1985
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0380
.42 linear feet
Biography/History
James Merrill Safford (1822-1907), an Ohio native attended Ohio University and Yale. He was famous for geological investigations of Tennessee, taught chemistry and biology, as well as geology. During his 52-year career, he was employed by Cumberland University, the University of Nashville, and Vanderbilt University. He also held the position of State Geologist of Tennessee. His professional contributions mainly consisted of survey work in geology throughout Tennessee. Later he mainly applied geology to health, agriculture, and resource development. His classic book and map, The Geology of Tennessee, appeared in 1869.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection contains 15 items. It includes biographical information, field notes on his geological work within the state of Tennessee, map etchings, financial expenses, and a diary.
- Biographical — (3)
  - Genealogy information, n.d.
  - Index cards, 1900
  - Journal Article, 1985
- Diary — (1)
  - 11/08/1901 — 02/06/1904
- Envelope — (1)
  - n.d.
- Newspaper Clipping — (1)
  - n.d.
- Notebooks — (7)
  - Field notes with geological sketches
  - 1889
  - 1890
  - 1891 — (2)
  - 1892
  - 1893
  - n.d.
- Voucher Books — (2)
  - Field notes with geological sketches
  - 1891 (2)